<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Westbury&#39;s Weblog.</title>
    <description>A place on the internet where you, dear reader, can peruse the inner machinations of my mind. Here you will find posts and essays on practical politics, coding and some philosophy &amp;amp; science.</description>
    <link>http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 12:51:56 +0000</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 12:51:56 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>I do apologise</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the last few weeks I have been completely snowed under by my relocation to Hertfordshire and the beginning of my new job. It’s been horrendously busy but I’m pretty excited that I’m finally actually making a contribution to modern civilisation (&lt;em&gt;read: making money&lt;/em&gt;). Unfortunately for you people, there are a couple of essays in the pipeline, one being a shameless plug for my pet project of an open think tank. Cheers for reading and all that, hopefully I’ll churn those essays out soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 28 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/09/28/an-apology.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/09/28/an-apology.html</guid>
        
        <category>Personal</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>We can legislate it for you wholesale</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Think Thanks. What are they? These institutions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some Think Tanks provide an invaluable service to policy and industry. For example, RUSI, a defence and foreign policy think tank, provides research into the future of warfare allowing the government and defense firms to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately many Think Tanks are run and backed by large corporate entities, this means that some of our most influential policy makers are in the pockets of the rich.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/23/openthinktank.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/23/openthinktank.html</guid>
        
        <category>Politics</category>
        
        <category>Democracy</category>
        
        <category>Crowd Sourcing</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Cooperative Manifesto</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;‘There is no such thing as society’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt; P(B|A) = \frac{P(A|B)}{P(A)}P(A) &lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is Maths working? It is now (fuck yeah)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;WORKERS OF THE WORLD, COOPERATE.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/23/cooperativemanifesto.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/23/cooperativemanifesto.html</guid>
        
        <category>Politics</category>
        
        <category>Cooperativism</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Bayes is best</title>
        <description>&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt; P(B|A) = \frac{P(A|B)}{P(A)}P(A) &lt;/script&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/23/bayesianjury.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/23/bayesianjury.html</guid>
        
        <category>Maths</category>
        
        <category>awesomeness</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Democracy, Directly</title>
        <description>    &lt;p&gt;Direct democracy has always been one of the main goals of the libertarian left but is often dismissed as an unattainable ideal. In this essay (the first in a series on practical politics), a model will be proposed for a practical system denoting not only the possibility of direct democracy but also the plausibility of its implementation in today’s world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a British perspective, contemporary democracy leaves a lot to be desired. The first-past-the-post system means that the British majority government can be voted in by a minority of voters (e.g. our current government only received 36.8% of the eligible public’s votes&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.economist.com/blogs/graphicdetail/2015/05/britain-s-election-2015-seats-votes-calculator&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;1&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.) and the lobbying system currently in place grants corporate voices far too much swaying power over legislation. This fact is reflected in current polls showing public opinion is in favour of renationalisation of energy suppliers and the railways&lt;a href=&quot;https://yougov.co.uk/news/2013/11/04/nationalise-energy-and-rail-companies-say-public/&quot;&gt;&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Democracy in the UK is in dire need of reform; it is evident that most ‘ordinary people’ do not have a say in how the country is run. This has led to a government that is not held accountable for actions that are mainly in the interest of corporate giants. A new democratic system that can both create more representative governments and hold legislators to account is therefore required. One proposed solution to these problems would be to create a democratic system based on tokens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-token-based-democracy&quot;&gt;A token based democracy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Token is the name given to a reusable form of vote. A token would be given to each eligible citizen in the country.  The proposed token-based democracy would require that each piece of legislation created by the legislators (e.g. the House of Commons) to be passed by the citizens of the country by placing their tokens on either the “yes” or “no” side or abstaining from the vote.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, a system this simple could not work in practice as the high frequency of bills being drafted would quickly lead to ever greater voter apathy, an argument usually given against direct democracy. Thanks to the nature of the token though, a way of reducing the amount of interference caused by constant legislation whilst still preserving individuals direct voting power is possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For convenience a voter can entrust their individual token to a political party (The word “party” is used here for familiarity, a party could be any person or organisation willing to vote on behalf of people). The party would then apply the token on votes for legislation on behalf of the voter. Crucially, to maintain direct democracy, the voter can move their token at any time. There would also be a provision made so that voters could use their token against the party they are with for specific bills. This would enable people who agree with the majority of a party’s policies, but have some issues close to their heart that contravene the party line, to have their ideals accounted for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this system let’s take a voter who has assigned their vote to the Green party but who is a strong advocate of nuclear power. When the legislators have a vote on a bill on nuclear power, the voter could place his token against the Green party’s vote. The amount of tokens that the Green party has is reduced by one for that vote but reverts for all votes that the voter is not voting against the entrusted party on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;cascading-proportional-representation&quot;&gt;Cascading Proportional Representation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The allocation of tokens to parties allows for, and naturally leads towards, a fluid form of the Proportional Representation voting system. This system would allocate seats in the house of legislators according to the amount of tokens each party holds every five (or so) years. This would ensure that the legislative House of Parliament would better reflect the views of the populace. The constituency system would be changed to a similar system to that used in the European Parliament today: there would be a number of MPs representing each constituency instead of just one. Unfortunately such a system would mean that MPs for smaller parties would be most likely placed in constituencies where the percentage of voters does not reflect the percentage of MPs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One solution to this problem would be to devolve more power to each level of government. Local government could then be structured and elected in the same way as the state government. This would streamline the voting system by doing away with the need for by-elections and would ensure that voters are properly represented in every level of government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-block-chain-technology-to-implement-tokens&quot;&gt;Using Block chain technology to implement tokens&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The block chain is the name given to the system that records transactions on the bitcoin network. In basic terms, the block chain acts as a ledger recording the most recent transactions in between bitcoin wallets. Therefore it provides a record of how many bitcoins each wallet holds and a means of transferring bitcoins between wallets.  For those interested, the original paper that proposed the Bitcoin system can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://bitcoin.org/bitcoin.pdf&quot;&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; The main motivation behind using a block chain like system  is the security provided: hackers attempting to falsify votes would need more computing power than the government’s systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bitcoin model would have to be modified to accommodate the requirements of the direct democratic system. There must be mechanisms for voting, entrusting tokens and relinquishing tokens. For anonymity, voters should be able to find out who their token is entrusted to, but the party shouldn’t be able to know, necessarily, who their tokens are from. Also there will have to be a mechanism for creating new tokens and parties (when people become eligible to vote) and, conversely, a mechanism for voiding tokens and parties (in the event of death/disbanding).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this essay has shown that direct democracy is possible in today’s world. At a later date I would like to write a further essay on the technical side of the implementation. If you have any suggestions, criticisms or opinions on this essay I wholeheartedly encourage you to leave your comments below.❑&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 21 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/21/bitcoin-democracy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://blog.cathxrsis.co.uk/2015/07/21/bitcoin-democracy.html</guid>
        
        <category>Bitcoin</category>
        
        <category>Democracy</category>
        
        <category>Politics</category>
        
        <category>Computer Science</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
